<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Universe OpenAstronomy (Posts about gsoc2022)</title><link>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/categories/cat_gsoc2022.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2022 01:14:24 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>week 11 and week 12</title><link>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2022/09/20220903_0000_supriya1702/</link><dc:creator>Supriya1702</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Now since fetching of extra columns which includes broadening coeffcients was completed I had to pull the the fetch_hitran_update changes…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="margin-top: 50px; font-style: italic;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://minimal-blog.lekoarts.de/week-11-and-week-12"&gt;Keep reading&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt;
&lt;!-- TEASER_END --&gt;</description><category>radis</category><guid>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2022/09/20220903_0000_supriya1702/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 02 Sep 2022 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>GSoC @ Stingray: Testing Testing Testing …</title><link>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2022/08/20220826_1631_mihirtripathi97/</link><dc:creator>Mihirtripathi</dc:creator><description>&lt;h4&gt;GSoC @ Stingray: Testing Testing Testing …&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;After getting the code for bexvar in working condition, the next task in front of me was to test the code. As I mentioned in the last blog I was completely new to software testing. This meant a lot of new things to learn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this blog, I am going to write about my experience with testing. This was one of the best learning experiences of my GSoC journey so far. With the help of my mentors, I arrived at the conclusion that primarily there are three kinds of tests that would be needed for bexvar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(1) Unit tests to check if various components of my code provide the correct outputs individually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- TEASER_END --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(2) Some functional tests to check if the entire bexvar() function works properly and gives the desired output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(3) Some other tests to check if proper warnings and errors are raised in the case of bad inputs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started with the unit tests. Creating the unit tests for internal functions was comparatively easy. Two of the three internal functions provided deterministic outputs. All that was needed for testing them was to calculate the desired output and compare it with the output from the code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the major problems arose while designing functional tests. The bexvar() function returns an array that contains the samples of the log of the bexvar (i.e. log(\sigma_{count rate})). These samples are proportional to the posterior distribution of log(\sigma_\{count rate}). These samples are generated by an MCMC generator and therefore the elements and the number of elements of the output array are different after each run for the same data. This makes testing the result more difficult as the elements of the array could not be compared with a predetermined result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the bexvar() aims to provide the posterior distribution of log(Sigma_\{count rate}) the elements as individuals do not matter but the shape of their histogram provides the posterior distribution. Therefore we decided to test the results with some statistical parameters derived from the generated samples which quantify the distribution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problems that I faced while designing the third type of test, helped me find and resolve multiple unseen issues with the code. It took me more time than I expected to complete the testing phase. However, I am glad to announce that the all tests are now passing successfully. Additionally, I also passed the mid-term evaluations! Phew!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At end of the testing phase, The &lt;a href="https://github.com/StingraySoftware/stingray/pull/664"&gt;PR&lt;/a&gt; was ready to be merged, after a few minor updates in the docstrings it was merged! Yaay! The work is not yet done though. Next, I am working to add a method to Stingray’s lightcurve class. In addition to this, I will be creating a tutorial page for using the bexvar and will also make some more improvements in the code if time permits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" height="1" src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&amp;amp;referrerSource=full_rss&amp;amp;postId=9d1572ac43ef" width="1"&gt;</description><category>stingray</category><guid>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2022/08/20220826_1631_mihirtripathi97/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2022 15:31:33 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>GSoC Blog #3</title><link>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2022/08/20220820_0702_aman-pandey-afk/</link><dc:creator>AMAN PANDEY</dc:creator><description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/680/1*dfjiDfMcY8h9eEOySAnxbA.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mid Evaluations are over, and I’m glad to be back at work. As the base functionality is done now, I am on to provide user APIs to create cross spectra and periodograms from actual astronomical data easily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was busy the first week after the mid-term due to intern season at my campus, so that I couldn’t contribute much. Afterward, I started by understanding different functionalities related to photon count events next week. The plan was to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Read the photon count data from different file formats and get the essential information like time, GTIs, PI channels, etc.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Create EventList struct and handle different methods like sorting, joining, filtering, and simulating these data.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Test these methods by appropriately re-binning, creating periodograms, and plotting the data.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;There was also modification in the git workflow as the documentation branch was based on the gti one, which now has its parent main.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- TEASER_END --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the 3rd week, I have worked on the EventList APIs and the data reading part. Its currently implemented for the FITS extension, but I will expand to other formats like HDF5 or ECSV. I have also studied LightCurve structure and implemented a to and from conversion with EventLists, although its methods are needed to be worked upon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the coming weeks, I aim to create extensive tests, debug these methods, and optimize them in Julia. After these are done, other features like coherence and time lags will also be necessary. The period will &lt;em&gt;end&lt;/em&gt; with documentation and refactoring of already existing codes, and &lt;em&gt;if&lt;/em&gt; I get time, I will work on variability vs. energy spectrum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" height="1" src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&amp;amp;referrerSource=full_rss&amp;amp;postId=350c7b7dad61" width="1"&gt;</description><category>stingray</category><guid>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2022/08/20220820_0702_aman-pandey-afk/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Aug 2022 06:02:40 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>week 9 and week 10</title><link>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2022/08/20220820_0000_supriya1702/</link><dc:creator>Supriya1702</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Dr. Erwan and Mr. Anand (my mentors) suggested since my Non-Air Diluent project was getting large I should first create a separate PR for…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="margin-top: 50px; font-style: italic;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://minimal-blog.lekoarts.de/week-9-and-week-10"&gt;Keep reading&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt;
&lt;!-- TEASER_END --&gt;</description><category>radis</category><guid>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2022/08/20220820_0000_supriya1702/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 19 Aug 2022 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>week 9 and week 10</title><link>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2022/08/20220816_0000_supriya1702/</link><dc:creator>Supriya1702</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Dr. Erwan and Mr. Anand (my mentors) suggested since my Non-Air Diluent project was getting large I should first create a separate PR for…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="margin-top: 50px; font-style: italic;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://minimal-blog.lekoarts.de/week-9-and-week-10"&gt;Keep reading&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt;
&lt;!-- TEASER_END --&gt;</description><category>radis</category><guid>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2022/08/20220816_0000_supriya1702/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 15 Aug 2022 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Welcome to Jekyll!</title><link>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2022/08/20220810_1030_sagarchotalia/</link><dc:creator>OpenAstronomy</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;You’ll find this post in your &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;jekyll serve&lt;/code&gt;, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll requires blog post files to be named according to the following format:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- TEASER_END --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;YEAR-MONTH-DAY-title.MARKUP&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;YEAR&lt;/code&gt; is a four-digit number, &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;MONTH&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;DAY&lt;/code&gt; are both two-digit numbers, and &lt;code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"&gt;MARKUP&lt;/code&gt; is the file extension representing the format used in the file. After that, include the necessary front matter. Take a look at the source for this post to get an idea about how it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll also offers powerful support for code snippets:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-ruby"&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;print_hi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nb"&gt;puts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;"Hi, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;#{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;print_hi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;'Tom'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="c1"&gt;#=&amp;gt; prints 'Hi, Tom' to STDOUT.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the &lt;a href="https://jekyllrb.com/docs/home"&gt;Jekyll docs&lt;/a&gt; for more info on how to get the most out of Jekyll. File all bugs/feature requests at &lt;a href="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll"&gt;Jekyll’s GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt;. If you have questions, you can ask them on &lt;a href="https://talk.jekyllrb.com/"&gt;Jekyll Talk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>radis</category><guid>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2022/08/20220810_1030_sagarchotalia/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2022 09:30:40 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>GSoC 2022: Project Helioviewer — Moving close to the First Release</title><link>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2022/08/20220810_0551_akash5100/</link><dc:creator>Akash</dc:creator><description>&lt;h4&gt;GSoC 2022: Project Helioviewer — Moving close to the First Release&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Week 7&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;The solution to switch the base URL of the python API wrapper got merged with PR &lt;a href="https://github.com/Helioviewer-Project/python-api/pull/41"&gt;#41&lt;/a&gt; and follow-up with PR &lt;a href="https://github.com/Helioviewer-Project/python-api/pull/44"&gt;#44&lt;/a&gt; by Nabil, now the next endpoint group was the movies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I rebased my old PR &lt;a href="https://github.com/Helioviewer-Project/python-api/pull/38"&gt;#38&lt;/a&gt; with the main branch, which brings the &lt;strong&gt;QueueMovie&lt;/strong&gt; endpoint, and opened &lt;a href="https://github.com/Helioviewer-Project/python-api/pull/51"&gt;#51&lt;/a&gt; which brings &lt;strong&gt;reQueueMovie&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;getMovieStatus &lt;/strong&gt;endpoint to facade and backend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the end of the week, both the PR is merged and we now focus on the documentation before the first release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- TEASER_END --&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Week 8&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started working on creating new &lt;strong&gt;RST&lt;/strong&gt; files (reStructuredText is a file format for textual data used primarily in the Python programming language community for technical documentation), writing developer's and installation documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With PR &lt;a href="https://github.com/Helioviewer-Project/python-api/pull/48"&gt;#48&lt;/a&gt;, the documentation for the first release is ready.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See the documentation here: &lt;a href="https://hvpy.readthedocs.io/en/latest/"&gt;https://hvpy.readthedocs.io/en/latest/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Week 9&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;The current &lt;strong&gt;hvpy&lt;/strong&gt; unittest tests the endpoint functions with the default API URL. But we also want to test the endpoint functions with the beta URL. Basically testing version 3 of the API before release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To achieve what we decided, we create an environment variable in the tox file, which triggers the function to &lt;em&gt;switch the base URL, &lt;/em&gt;and now all the test in tox runs in the beta URL.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;PR &lt;a href="https://github.com/Helioviewer-Project/python-api/pull/55"&gt;#55&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="1" src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&amp;amp;referrerSource=full_rss&amp;amp;postId=c43249d042d9" width="1"&gt;</description><category>SunPy</category><guid>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2022/08/20220810_0551_akash5100/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2022 04:51:50 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Advanced options</title><link>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2022/07/20220731_0000_arunavabasu-03/</link><dc:creator>arunavabasu-03</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Impove default resolution of ploted spectrum In  wstep = “auto”  radis app gives slitly low res. for that reasons plotted  spectrum  is…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="margin-top: 50px; font-style: italic;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://minimal-blog.lekoarts.de/6thweek/"&gt;Keep reading&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt;
&lt;!-- TEASER_END --&gt;</description><category>radis</category><guid>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2022/07/20220731_0000_arunavabasu-03/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 30 Jul 2022 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>week 7 and week 8 (Mid-Term Evaluation!)</title><link>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2022/07/20220730_0000_supriya1702/</link><dc:creator>Supriya1702</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Now, this week was the Mid-Term Evaluation week and I was totally nervous about it. I knew that I had put alot of efforts and time into the…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="margin-top: 50px; font-style: italic;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://minimal-blog.lekoarts.de/week-7-and-week-8-mid-term-evaluation"&gt;Keep reading&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt;
&lt;!-- TEASER_END --&gt;</description><category>radis</category><guid>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2022/07/20220730_0000_supriya1702/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 29 Jul 2022 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>GSoC Blog#2</title><link>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2022/07/20220726_0559_aman-pandey-afk/</link><dc:creator>AMAN PANDEY</dc:creator><description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/680/1*dfjiDfMcY8h9eEOySAnxbA.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first half of the coding period is almost done, and here I am with the updates! As stated at the end of the last blog, I started the 3rd week by improving the &lt;a href="https://github.com/StingraySoftware/Stingray.jl/pull/2"&gt;second PR&lt;/a&gt;. I performed pretty intensive memory and performance analysis on the functions in fourier.jl, using BenchmarkTools and .mem files to analyze bottlenecks in the program. With my mentors’ help, I removed many allocation and type-stability related issues during that time. I also had some problems with non-idiomatic code, like I could use multiple-dispatch or dot broadcast in functions, some of which I solved, and some are due for refactoring after the mid-evaluation. After finishing the improvements and getting my second PR merged, I planned to work on LightCurves and implement periodograms and other APIs so that users can easily manipulate photon count data. But my mentor suggested I implement file reading and mechanisms to manage the GTIs (Good Time Intervals) obtained from these files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Working out the GTI mechanisms&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had learned a lot from the previous PR, and one of the things was I should try to implement some of the methods in my way rather than using the python algorithms with an idiomatic Julian code in mind. I started the 4th week with methods for reading GTIs from a FITS file (For those unfamiliar, it is a file format for storing, processing, and transmitting scientific data, especially images). I used the FITSIO.jl package, and experimenting on the terminal led me to manipulate HDUs and their data. One thing I thoroughly thought of was the appropriate data structure of the GTIs. Should I use Intervals from the Intervals.jl package? Or a vector of vector like the python library does? I finally decided to use what I was using in the fourier.jl, an AbstractMatrix of Reals. It was easy to access data from them, and you could use slices to get a list of start and end times. For the operations, I had to convert among matrix, intervals frequently, and vectors as the Intervals.jl provided many ways to manipulate GTIs like union or intersection or getting its complement, i.e., Bad Time Intervals. With some more methods like creating masks and GTIs from conditions and implementing Tests for all of these functions, I was finished with the gti.jl file. A little performance analysis told me that the code was efficient. After some refactoring, like removing code duplication by merging union and intersection in the same function, I was done with the PR. It has some minor changes currently to be made before it gets merged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- TEASER_END --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Working on the documentation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*lbM1DS0_-Ja0lb53Owb6PQ.png"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the mid evaluations have begun this week, I will be taking some time to write the docstring and deploy them on GitHub. The stingray python docs are pretty good, so I will mostly use them as a Base and tweak them as necessary (when there is a different function signature or the Julian way of doing things is different). Documenter.jl will be the package I would be using for this. The complete documentation will be a milestone for the end of the program, where I, along with my mentors, will try to write notebook tutorials for the package and host them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For the second phase&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope to qualify for the mid-evals, after which the second phase will begin. The core implementation is done; users can now use the library and its different methods to read from a file, process the data, and create periodograms. The main motive now will be to ease its access and implement other helpful features, a major one of which will be plotting the periodograms. I initially proposed working with these APIs before mid-evals, but who knows about the future? I have done some things meant for the other half, so I guess it’s okay. As an end note, I am pretty much excited for the other half of this program, it has made me learn a lot, and the workings of Julia awe-inspire me as I explore it side by side. Goodbye for now!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" height="1" src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&amp;amp;referrerSource=full_rss&amp;amp;postId=63d283e1a60b" width="1"&gt;</description><category>stingray</category><guid>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2022/07/20220726_0559_aman-pandey-afk/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 26 Jul 2022 04:59:13 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>