<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Universe OpenAstronomy (Posts about stingray)</title><link>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/categories/stingray.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 02:21:45 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Oops, I’m a GSoC Dev Now?</title><link>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2025/06/20250604_1803_adnan-itis/</link><dc:creator>Mohammad Adnan</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Wow! I still can't believe I'm actually in Google Summer of Code! This was a dream, and now here I am, officially past the Community Bonding Period and diving headfirst into the Coding Phase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;What’s Happening Right Now?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now, I’m sketching out the basic structure of the application interface. The first big task? Fetching event files from specific sources. Sounds simple, right? Well… not quite&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- TEASER_END --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turns out, HEASARC (the database I need) is having a little meltdown (don’t we all sometimes?). So while I wait for it to get its act together, I’ve been tweaking the pipeline that’ll handle the data retrieval.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, and my mentor dropped a fun suggestion: "Hey, why not try running this on SciServer?" So guess what I’ll be wrestling with next? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last two weeks were chaos. My end-semester exams decided to crash the party right in the middle of the Community Bonding Period. Juggling study sessions, meeting my mentors, and trying not to panic about code I hadn’t even written yet? Yeah, that was… an experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I survived! And soon, I’ll spill all the tea in a proper "How I Got Into GSoC" post—complete with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why I chose Stingray &lt;b&gt;(spoiler: space data is cool)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The emotional rollercoaster of the application process&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why I may or may not have happy-cried when I got accepted&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;What’s Next? Big Dreams &amp;amp; Messy Code&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve got so many ideas for this project, and the best part? We’re still figuring things out as we go. It’s like exploring uncharted territory—sometimes you hit a wall, sometimes you find a hidden shortcut, but it’s always an adventure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is my very first GSoC blog, and honestly? I’m just excited to share the journey—bugs, breakthroughs, and all. Thanks for reading! More updates coming soon. 🚀 :})&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>stingray</category><guid>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2025/06/20250604_1803_adnan-itis/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 17:03:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Submission done finally</title><link>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2024/08/20240826_1626_kartikmandar/</link><dc:creator>Kartik Mandar</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt; Damn it was an eventful 3-4 months, from crying to why the code is not working to enjoying the small success of getting the plots. I am grateful that I got the opportunity to be in GSOC and get to know the wonderful mentors Matteo and Gullo. Thank you for guiding me. Let's see what the final term evaluation beholds for me..Fingers crossed. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Also regardless of how the evaluation turns out to be, I am gonna continue contributing to the project as much as I can. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- TEASER_END --&gt;</description><category>stingray</category><guid>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2024/08/20240826_1626_kartikmandar/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2024 15:26:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Almost done</title><link>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2024/08/20240823_1648_kartikmandar/</link><dc:creator>Kartik Mandar</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt; Project is almost going to end currently, but there are so many plans for the future. I am gonna keep contributing in the future and make this a project a worthwhile tool for the astronomers to use. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- TEASER_END --&gt;</description><category>stingray</category><guid>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2024/08/20240823_1648_kartikmandar/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2024 15:48:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Float Panels working but there's a catch</title><link>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2024/08/20240814_1709_kartikmandar/</link><dc:creator>Kartik Mandar</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt; Finally everything is working on floating panels and the dashboard is so much customisable now! It's awesome. But as every good thing has a catch, all my HoloViews objects are synced now, I don't yet know what the issue is but I have to figure this out!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- TEASER_END --&gt;</description><category>stingray</category><guid>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2024/08/20240814_1709_kartikmandar/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Aug 2024 16:09:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Changing the plotting methods</title><link>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2024/08/20240805_1605_kartikmandar/</link><dc:creator>Kartik Mandar</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt; So the recoding and redesign is done. But we were discussing about how we are plotting things in dashboard and wanted to have floatpanels for doing so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- TEASER_END --&gt;</description><category>stingray</category><guid>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2024/08/20240805_1605_kartikmandar/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 05 Aug 2024 15:05:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Issue resolved</title><link>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2024/07/20240725_1809_kartikmandar/</link><dc:creator>Kartik Mandar</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt; The problem with classes was resolved by making factory functions to encase them in, and then they were not conflicting with each other. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- TEASER_END --&gt;</description><category>stingray</category><guid>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2024/07/20240725_1809_kartikmandar/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2024 17:09:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>New issue propped up</title><link>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2024/07/20240718_1634_kartikmandar/</link><dc:creator>Kartik Mandar</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt; When changing the whole architecture, a new issue has propped. An initialised object of the class can not be initialised again. So I am not able to revert back the home UI back dynamically. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- TEASER_END --&gt;</description><category>stingray</category><guid>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2024/07/20240718_1634_kartikmandar/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2024 15:34:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Finally the issue resolves</title><link>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2024/07/20240715_1528_kartikmandar/</link><dc:creator>Kartik Mandar</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt; Damn, those 2 weeks were stressful, finally the issue is resolved. I am able to render HoloViews and thus Bokeh plots inside my program and in the process my codebase is much better than before. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- TEASER_END --&gt;</description><category>stingray</category><guid>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2024/07/20240715_1528_kartikmandar/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2024 14:28:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Refactoring the codebase</title><link>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2024/07/20240711_1548_kartikmandar/</link><dc:creator>Kartik Mandar</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt; I am refactoring the whole codebase to make it more maintainable and in that hoping to solve the issue with HoloViews. I am making the codebase fully pragmatic and declarative and using Parameterised classes. I hope so it resolves the issue with HoloViews. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- TEASER_END --&gt;</description><category>stingray</category><guid>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2024/07/20240711_1548_kartikmandar/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2024 14:48:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Watching the tutorials in depth</title><link>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2024/07/20240709_1716_kartikmandar/</link><dc:creator>Kartik Mandar</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt; I am facing a serious bug now, I can't render bokeh plots at all. HoloViews objects is not able to render anything out at all. I have to find the solution because our whole project depends on HoloViews objects and its capabilities. Otherwise we are just plotting simple matplotlib plots. So currently I am going through the tutorials and documentation of all HoloViz ecosystem, be it Panel, or HoloViews or hvplot in detail. I am hoping to find the solution, maybe raise the issue through github, as I have seen some similar issue with people in the github issues of Panel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- TEASER_END --&gt;</description><category>stingray</category><guid>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2024/07/20240709_1716_kartikmandar/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2024 16:16:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>