<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Universe OpenAstronomy (Posts by Lucas Martin Garcia)</title><link>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/authors/lucas-martin-garcia.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2024 01:04:05 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Filling the Temporal Gaps in AGN Light Curve Data</title><link>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2024/06/20240630_2331_lucasmg18/</link><dc:creator>Lucas Martin Garcia</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Introduction to the Challenge&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our ongoing quest to understand Active Galactic Nuclei (AGNs), handling the discontinuous nature of AGN light curve data remains the main goal. The gaps in observation data, caused by unavoidable operational and environmental constraints, obscure the complete picture of these AGN data. To address several methods are taken into account to approach the temporal data interpolation, combining traditional techniques with advanced machine learning models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Traditional Interpolation Techniques&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- TEASER_END --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The basic Interpolation Methods include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Linear Interpolation:&lt;/strong&gt; Useful for filling short gaps where changes between points are expected to be gradual and linear.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Polynomial Interpolation:&lt;/strong&gt; Offers a more flexible approach for non-linear data, providing smoother estimates that can better reflect inherent variabilities in AGN light emissions.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;These techniques are fast and effective for smaller, simpler gaps but often fall short when dealing with larger or more complex interruptions in data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advanced Machine Learning Techniques&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more substantial gaps or when high fidelity to complex light curve dynamics is crucial, some machine learning algorithms are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recurrent Neural Networks (RNNs):&lt;/strong&gt; These are particularly adept at modeling time-series data, capturing dependencies across time steps to predict missing observations with a high degree of accuracy.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Generative Adversarial Networks (GANs):&lt;/strong&gt; By training GANs on existing data, we can generate new data points that not only fill larger gaps but also maintain statistical consistency with observed data.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Moving Forward&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The integration of these methods has already shown promising results in other fields and applications. As we refine these techniques, we aim not only to improve the quality of data but also to deepen our understanding of the underlying physical processes of AGNs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our journey into the light curves of AGNs is as much about improving our observational tools and techniques as it is about exploring the universe's mysteries. By bridging these data gaps, we hope to bring clarity to the complexities of galaxy evolution and contribute to the broader astronomical community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The challenge of incomplete data is not unique to astronomy but is a common issue in various scientific domains. Our interdisciplinary approach has obtained already good results in other fields where data integrity impacts the quality of research outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>irsa-fornax</category><guid>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2024/06/20240630_2331_lucasmg18/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 30 Jun 2024 22:31:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Tackling the Challenges of Active Galactic Nuclei Data with Machine Learning Models</title><link>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2024/06/20240623_2331_lucasmg18/</link><dc:creator>Lucas Martin Garcia</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Understanding the Complexity of AGN Light Curve Data&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Active Galactic Nuclei (AGNs) are among the most luminous and dynamic objects in the universe, characterized by their variable light emissions that provide key insights into the mechanics of galaxy evolution. A fundamental challenge in studying AGNs is the nature of the data collected where the parameters such as time and wavelength are critical. Each observation captures the light curve of an AGN.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, this data isn't straightforward. Observations are taken using different instruments, like different stations or satellites, leading to variations in data quality and measurement techniques. More critically, there are inevitable gaps in the data, caused by factors ranging from environmental conditions blocking observations to the simple fact that different tools have different operational time frames and capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- TEASER_END --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Goal: Enhancing Data Cohesiveness&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The objective of our research project is clear: to enhance the cohesiveness and quality of AGN light curve datasets. This involves not only unifying data across different wavelengths and time periods but also filling in missing data to create a more complete picture of AGN activity. The challenge is non-trivial, as it requires sophisticated approaches to accurately interpolate or simulate missing observations without distorting the underlying physical phenomena.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advanced Machine Learning Models for Data Enhancement&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To address these challenges, we are exploring several machine learning (ML) models. Deep learning (DL) models, particularly neural networks, are at the forefront of our tools, owing to their ability to model complex patterns and dependencies in large datasets. Recurrent Neural Networks (RNNs) are particularly suited for this task because of their effectiveness in handling sequential data, which is a natural fit for time-series analysis like light curves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, Generative Adversarial Networks (GANs) offer a promising approach to generate new data points synthetically. GANs can be trained to produce data that mimics the statistical properties of existing observations, potentially filling gaps in the light curves with high accuracy. These models learn to simulate new data that could plausibly occur under similar conditions, based on the patterns learned from the data that do exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Moving Forward&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our research is still in the developmental phase, with ongoing efforts to refine the models and enhance their predictive and generative capabilities. By integrating these advanced ML models, we aim to not only improve the data quality of AGN observations but also to provide deeper insights into their dynamic behavior, which remains an enigma in many aspects. This could significantly aid astronomers and astrophysicists in understanding the fundamental processes driving these powerful celestial objects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By leveraging the power of machine learning we hope to overcome the significant problems posed by the fragmented and incomplete nature of AGN light curve data. This research not only pushes the boundaries of astronomical data analysis but also contributes to the broader field of applied machine learning in solving real-world problems with high complexity and significant scientific impact.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>irsa-fornax</category><guid>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2024/06/20240623_2331_lucasmg18/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2024 22:31:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Starting the Project</title><link>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2024/06/20240609_1208_lucasmg18/</link><dc:creator>Lucas Martin Garcia</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;We are excited to start this project at the intersection of artificial intelligence and astronomy hosted by the Google Summer of Code (GSoC) program and work with the incredible team at OpenAstronomy. This project, which focuses on leveraging advanced data processing and deep learning models to enhance astronomical research, represents a unique opportunity to bridge the gap between data science and astronomy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am eager to contribute my skills and enthusiasm aiming to tackle the complexities of diverse astronomical datasets. Working with the dedicated professionals at OpenAstronomy, I am confident that we will make significant strides in advancing the field and promoting the principles of open science and collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Together, we will push the boundaries of what is possible in astronomical research, paving the way for new discoveries and fostering a more inclusive and accessible scientific community. I look forward to the exciting journey ahead and the work we will accomplish as a team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- TEASER_END --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEjQc7ZKtKEemrWEqavXXHEAD2JI6FI89n0TRIHmKscmvPuhtD8IvbbfAD0sK86EUXohESyvP4IaxNsaqm9ef_KAWMpEGeOsSt3KtIjOg5ba7UDW_b6QvOgDgtDfQ-Er03Jug0j75PrF8f8Dec0EhdJEOqrM6Er2RnSV52f-QGz7kg1AlaIhq_Xy7IzLQceh/s1000/logo%202.png" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="40" src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEjQc7ZKtKEemrWEqavXXHEAD2JI6FI89n0TRIHmKscmvPuhtD8IvbbfAD0sK86EUXohESyvP4IaxNsaqm9ef_KAWMpEGeOsSt3KtIjOg5ba7UDW_b6QvOgDgtDfQ-Er03Jug0j75PrF8f8Dec0EhdJEOqrM6Er2RnSV52f-QGz7kg1AlaIhq_Xy7IzLQceh/s320/logo%202.png" width="320"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/a/AVvXsEh53ytB8I6bARNOlCFfADd99BWyQIbg4C6QfWBNFnmvInwwADbdYQUkzRcmeKV8kfzJY_wvtZRBvx62ng6miFSeaq2gSfrYM9IaMEHhPmwlhsiuIy7lF5TR7GkdRQMmXb3RcvVIU1KYt1hfMXgmtrdIJ4B2H_SdGQNJRgGWcwOjczkrSoLpK26u2M8GPci7" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img alt="" height="154" src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/a/AVvXsEh53ytB8I6bARNOlCFfADd99BWyQIbg4C6QfWBNFnmvInwwADbdYQUkzRcmeKV8kfzJY_wvtZRBvx62ng6miFSeaq2gSfrYM9IaMEHhPmwlhsiuIy7lF5TR7GkdRQMmXb3RcvVIU1KYt1hfMXgmtrdIJ4B2H_SdGQNJRgGWcwOjczkrSoLpK26u2M8GPci7" width="320"&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;span style="color: #0000ee;"&gt;&lt;u&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;span style="color: #0000ee;"&gt;&lt;u&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>irsa-fornax</category><guid>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2024/06/20240609_1208_lucasmg18/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 09 Jun 2024 11:08:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>