<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Universe OpenAstronomy (Posts by Rachitt Shah)</title><link>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/authors/rachitt-shah.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 09 Oct 2022 01:14:00 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>The first weeks of X-Rays and Electron.Js</title><link>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2021/06/20210620_1829_rachittshah/</link><dc:creator>Rachitt Shah</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Python, X-rays, and JSON files that don’t comply and make you cry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GSoC has officially started!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/498/0*AXMzJYLpLP0sFPgE"&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;We’re going to code!&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since is a Desktop App made with Electron and Python, my first priority was getting DAVE to compile again. The process was tedious and took a good amount of time to fix the flask backends which power DAVE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- TEASER_END --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another error that came while getting DAVE up was that DAVE uses Stingray’s APIs which are lower than 2.0, which gave a lot of broken packages. Fixing this was something that would be covered in the POC enhancements, however, it was important to tackle this to build the MVP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looked at some major changes in the coming 0.3 for Stingray and how to accommodate them, so we don’t have issues later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Had exams alongside, so the first week was less effort extensive for GSoC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Waiting for the next week to write more about my progress and journey!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" height="1" src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&amp;amp;referrerSource=full_rss&amp;amp;postId=84f7557d97a7" width="1"&gt;</description><category>stingray</category><guid>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2021/06/20210620_1829_rachittshah/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 20 Jun 2021 17:29:09 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Summer of Coding and Astronomy — GSoC’21 at OpenAstronomy</title><link>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2021/06/20210607_1403_rachittshah/</link><dc:creator>Rachitt Shah</dc:creator><description>&lt;h4&gt;A Summer of Coding and Astronomy — GSoC’21 at OpenAstronomy&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/400/0*5kDNG2NTio40EKZh.gif"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;h4&gt;“In real open source, you have the right to control your own destiny.”&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;— Linus Torvalds&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google Summer of Code is probably the most notable and interesting programs a student can be a part of an undergrad can be a part of. From reading GSoC blogs to write my story, it feels unnatural.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is more of an introduction to GSoC and my project at OpenAstronomy, I’ll be covering my prep and journey later on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- TEASER_END --&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;About my GSoC project!&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/0*VCNaN41xLMATNTgC"&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;The DAVE engine!&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Generating periodograms for astronomical data is the core task of Stingray. Because periodograms are often noisy, several methods to denoise periodograms exist in the literature, among them the multi-taper periodogram Stingray aims to provide a comprehensive library of reliable, well-tested implementations of common algorithms for time series analysis in Astronomy. DAVE is an elegant GUI to the library, developed during a previous GSoC.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Due to the fast-evolving Python and Javascript landscape, this GUI is not compatible with the current versions of the dependencies. Also, Stingray has now new features that were not implemented in the original GUI.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;In this project, I would be refreshing the GUI dependencies, update the package building infrastructure, and add the new functionality introduced in recent versions of Stingray.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;I would be making sure DAVE would be up and running again over the summer, couldn’t have been happier!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;About me&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’m Rachitt Shah, a second-year undergrad at VIT Pune. I’m also doing Google Season of Docs with the STE||AR group for their project HPX.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m a growth associate at gradCapital, a student-centric VC fund that aims to help student startups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love product management, tech(of course!) and venture capital.&lt;br&gt;Here’s my social profiles link -&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/rachittshah"&gt;https://twitter.com/rachittshah&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/rachitt-shah/"&gt;https://www.linkedin.com/in/rachitt-shah/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have any questions about open-source and dev, don’t hesitate to reach out. &lt;br&gt;May the source be with you!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" height="1" src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&amp;amp;referrerSource=full_rss&amp;amp;postId=a7d716df482e" width="1"&gt;</description><category>stingray</category><guid>http://openastronomy.org/Universe_OA/posts/2021/06/20210607_1403_rachittshah/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 07 Jun 2021 13:03:09 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>